const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",o="civiledu",i=200,t=120,a=[{id:56,question:"The most effective approach towards the elimination of sexually transmitted diseases is by",option:{a:"abstinence.",b:"Casual sex.",c:"use of condom.",d:"use of drugs"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:214,question:"Which of the following concepts confirms the general acceptance and recognition of a government?",option:{a:"Democratic powers",b:"Legitimacy",c:"sovereignty",d:"popular democracy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:78,question:"Public Complaints Commission in Nigeria is also known as",option:{a:"elder’s forum.",b:"judiciary.",c:"ombudsman.",d:"people’s court."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:128,question:"One of the following is not a pressure group",option:{a:"National Association of Nigeria Student (NANS)",b:"Nigeria Labour Congress (NLC)",c:"Academic Staff Union of Universities (ASUU)",d:"Committee for Defense of Human Right (CDHR)"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:323,question:"Naira and Kobo was introduced in Nigeria in ..............",option:{a:"2nd July,1963",b:"1st January 1972",c:"June 12, 1993",d:"March13, 1995"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:366,question:"Which of the following is not a means of reducing the incidence of HIV/AIDS in our society?",option:{a:"Education and enlightenment programs",b:"The use of specially designed cutlery by victims",c:"Avoiding pre-marital and extra-marital sex",d:"Upholding the value of chastity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:297,question:"HIV and Ebola can be contacted through contact with",option:{a:"Non infected person",b:"contaminated medical equipment such as needles and syringes",c:"Very sick person",d:"Healthy reptiles"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:308,question:"The number of Girls abducted by members of Boko Haram at Chibok in 2014 is roughly",option:{a:"200",b:"219",c:"419",d:"180"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:328,question:"The full meaning of NYSC is ..............",option:{a:"Now Your Suffering Continues",b:"Nigeria Youths Serving Christ",c:"National Youth Service Corps",d:"Nigerian Youth Service Corps"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:435,question:"It could be inferred from the dialogue that failure to vote in an election would",option:{a:"guarantee citizens’ rights",b:"encourage the emergence of responsive government",c:"promote accountability in governance",d:"perpetuate irresponsible leadership"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:173,question:"In a democratic government, political sovereignty is vested in the",option:{a:"legislature",b:"elite",c:"executive",d:"electorate"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:182,question:"A manifesto refers to",option:{a:"the register of party members",b:"rejected ballot papers",c:"valid ballot papers",d:"Document containing the aims and programmes of   a political party"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:316,question:"Which of the following is the cleanest source of water in Nigeria",option:{a:"pond water",b:"river water",c:"rain water",d:"lagoon water"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:186,question:"The lack of interest in politics by many citizens in a country is called",option:{a:"civic agitation",b:"mass apathy",c:"mass protest",d:"political unrest"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:156,question:"Workers in the Public Corporations are known as",option:{a:"Civil servants",b:"Private employees",c:"Public servants",d:"Professional employees"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:430,question:"Nationalism ensures the following except",option:{a:"national consciousness",b:"secession in a country",c:"national integration",d:"unity in a country"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:412,question:"From the above write-up what category of Kantoguan youth deserves to be effectively empowered?",option:{a:"Children of the ruling political class",b:"Unemployed youths and school drop-outs",c:"University undergraduates",d:"Youth wing of religious organizations"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:270,question:"During a particular voting exercise if majority of the 	people refuse to vote, this can be described as",option:{a:"political stubbornness",b:"political apathy",c:"political awareness",d:"political socialization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:210,question:"For which of these can someone be arrested while driving on a high way",option:{a:"driving and laughing",b:"driving and singing",c:"driving and eating or receiving phone call",d:"driving and crying"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:84,question:"Which of the following is not a function of political parties?",option:{a:"Aggregation of opinion",b:"Educating the government",c:"Interest articulation",d:"Unifying factor."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:12,question:"Youth empowerment is best described as the",option:{a:"training given to individuals for acquiring means livelihood",b:"practice of engaging in prospective career",c:"provision of subsidized meals to the citizens by government,",d:"mobilization of citizens for political rally."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:351,question:"“We the people of the Federal Republic of Nigeria” is usually the opening phrase of the preamble to",option:{a:"coup announcement",b:"government gazettes",c:"constitution",d:"mansard"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:354,question:"Citizenship education influences an individual to be",option:{a:"patriotic",b:"educated",c:"complacent",d:"competent"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:414,question:"Based on the write-up, what immediate measures can those in authority take to empower the youths?",option:{a:"Build more youth orientation camps in the country",b:"Enhance religious and moral education in schools and colleges",c:"Provide entrepreneurial training with adequate fund",d:"Provide free meal for the teeming unemployed youths"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:198,question:"The primary duty of the police force is to",option:{a:"Make law",b:"Interpret the law",c:"Deal with danfo and okada drivers",d:"Non of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:62,question:"Franchise means right to",option:{a:"contest for political post",b:"join association",c:"live in Nigeria",d:"vote and be voted for"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:13,question:"The National Assembly, Presidency and Court which are inter - related and interdependent in our democracy constitute the",option:{a:"tiers of government",b:"types of democracy",c:"forms of government.",d:"arms of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:370,question:"Rule of law is limited by the following except",option:{a:"state of emergency",b:"habeas corpus",c:"illiteracy",d:"immunity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:192,question:"Colonization of Africa was mainly motivated by",option:{a:"security consideration",b:"economic reasons",c:"religious reasons",d:"cultural factor"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:17,question:"In Nigeria, public servants are expected to be",option:{a:"non - partisan",b:"political",c:"ambitious",d:"apolitical"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:421,question:"Association and affiliation between two or more people is called",option:{a:"multilateral relations",b:"bilateral relations",c:"inter-communal relations",d:"interpersonal relations"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:188,question:"The following are examples of pressure group except",option:{a:"N. U. R. T",b:"NBA",c:"NLC",d:"PDP"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:422,question:"A bill passed by the National Assembly requires the assent of the president before it becomes law. The law can be declared null and void by the court of law. The process above emphasizes the",option:{a:"supremacy of judiciary over other arms of government",b:"relationship among the arms of government",c:"importance of law makers in a democracy",d:"fundamentals of the rule of law."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:131,question:"The organization with the motives and goals of helping people is called",option:{a:"social group",b:"charity group",c:"pressure group",d:"human right group"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:11,question:"One habit which People Living With HIV/AIDS (PLWHAs) must avoid to remain healthy and productive is",option:{a:"regular contact with healthy people.",b:"self - pity and self - medication",c:"participation in profitable ventures",d:"pursuit of academic studies."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:215,question:"Which of the following can cause Human Trafficking in a country",option:{a:"poverty, youth unemployment and greed",b:"Sound education and proper counselling",c:"Social and economic contentment",d:"B and C above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:106,question:"One of the listed criteria qualifies one for election .......",option:{a:"certificate",b:"beauty",c:"height",d:"citizenship"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:184,question:"The police perform all the following function except",option:{a:"public execution of law breaker",b:"controlling and directing traffic",c:"protection of life and property",d:"enforcement of law and orders"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:303,question:"As at 2014 Nigeria has .......... states",option:{a:"47",b:"37",c:"60",d:"57"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:172,question:"A constitution that is very easy to amend is called a ...... constitution",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"an easy",d:"simple"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:114,question:"Cocaine, morphine and heroin are example of",option:{a:"tobacco",b:"steroids",c:"narcotics",d:"inhalants"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:102,question:"There are ............. local government in Nigeria",option:{a:"700",b:"714",c:"744",d:"774"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:420,question:"Effective and responsible parenthood is primarily",option:{a:"a national duty",b:"a military duty",c:"a political duty",d:"an economic duty"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:388,question:"Citizen’s compliance with tenets of the Nigerian National Pledge will enable the country to",option:{a:"receive reciprocal assistance",b:"witness value clarification",c:"get international aid",d:"experience development"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:306,question:"Which of the following is a bad habit capable of leading to future psychological and physiological ill health",option:{a:"self Actualization",b:"Self Meditation",c:"Self Medication",d:"Self Appraisal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:263,question:"In which of the following system is survival of the fittest mostly practiced",option:{a:"Communist system",b:"Capitalist system",c:"Feudalist",d:"Totalistic system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:10,question:"Victims of human trafficking are usually compelled to engage in",option:{a:"lucrative employment",b:"visiting tourist sites",c:"part - time studies",d:"forced labour."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:57,question:"The first executive president of Nigeria is/was",option:{a:"Abubakar Tafawa Balewa",b:"Goodluck Jonathan",c:"NnamdiAzikiwe.",d:"Shehu Shagari."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:318,question:"Which of the following was a former military head of state in Nigeria",option:{a:"MKO Abiola",b:"Goodluck Jonathan",c:"General Idiagbon",d:"General Babagida"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:177,question:"A government is said to be legitimate if it",option:{a:"has the people’s mandate to rule",b:"is not oppressive",c:"provide social services for the people",d:"accepts people’s criticism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:365,question:"Drug law enforcement agencies in Nigeria are not empowered to",option:{a:"execute drug suspects",b:"arrest drug barons",c:"prosecute drug traffickers",d:"rehabilitate drug addicts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:5,question:"Human Rights are basic natural rights which people enjoy primarily because they are",option:{a:"members of a political party",b:"international citizens",c:"members of a community",d:"human beings."},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:405,question:"A major way of promoting responsible parenthood is through",option:{a:"sex education",b:"sound education",c:"population control measures",d:"tax reduction measures"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:282,question:"Psychopathy is a form of ................ behaviour",option:{a:"Normal",b:"abnormal",c:"desired",d:"valued"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:401,question:"An ideology that aims at promoting national consciousness and identity is",option:{a:"nationalism",b:"socialization",c:"civic culture",d:"progressivism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:116,question:"Cannabis is also called .........",option:{a:"barbiturates",b:"cassava",c:"marijuana",d:"caffeine"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:47,question:"Which of the following is not a function of the Independent National Electoral Commission (INEC)?",option:{a:"Administering oath of office to elected officers",b:"Conducting periodic elections",c:"Recruitment of electoral officers.",d:"Registration of political parties"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:419,question:"The above quotation summarizes the",option:{a:"Universal Declaration of Human Rights.",b:"African Charter on Human Rights.",c:"Geneva Conventions and Protocols.",d:"United Nations Organization Charter."},section:"“All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and rights. They are endowed with reason and 		conscience and should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood”.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:16,question:"The division of Nigeria into various constituencies with each electing a person to represent it in the National Assembly is a demonstration of",option:{a:"checks and balances",b:"popular participation",c:"political rivalry among the constituents",d:"drive towards secession in the country."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:338,question:"On the 18th of November 2014 in Yobe, some crowds lynched a suspected suicide bomber. The action of the crowd is .....",option:{a:"right because ‘he who kills by the sword must die by the sword’",b:"wrong because they have unlawfully taken the law into their hands, they should have handed the suicide  bomber over to the police",c:"right because we all have to fights against all forms of terrorism",d:"right so that others will learn lesson from this action"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:331,question:"Those eligible to partake in the scheme are those",option:{a:"Those seeking for admission into the higher institutions",b:"Who have successfully completed their studies from higher institution .eg. college of education, 		     polytechnic & university",c:"Who are looking for something to keep them busy",d:"Who are from poor family background"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:20,question:"According to the story, Imoh’s parents were",option:{a:"wealthy couple",b:"prominent politicians",c:"honest and responsible",d:"religious fanatics"},section:"Imoh lived with her parents in Kakuri. They were good citizens who detested all forms of immoral acts. Both at home and in school, Imoh had been taught the virtues and values of a good citizen. However, while in a bus on her way home from school, the conductor forgot to ask for her fare. She knew that the right thing to do was to pay even when the conductor had forgotten to collect the fare. She also knew that there were other things she could do with the money if it was not paid, but she did what was expected by informing the conductor and paying the fare.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:423,question:"The idea that “Law should be impartial with the people who break it” implies",option:{a:"principle of fair hearing",b:"right to legal representation",c:"equality before the law",d:"prerogative writ of habeas corpus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:141,question:"The traffic light has how many colours",option:{a:"3",b:"4",c:"5",d:"2"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:248,question:"The primary function of the legislature is the",option:{a:"monitoring the executive",b:"making of laws",c:"voting of bills",d:"appointment of ministers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:197,question:".............. was the capital of Nigeria before .................",option:{a:"Abuja - Lagos",b:"Lagos - Abuja",c:"Ikeja - Abuja",d:"Benin - Abuja"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:9,question:"It could be inferred from the statements above that cultism in schools could lead to",option:{a:"sudden prosperity.",b:"uninterrupted academic calender.",c:"popularity on campus.",d:"untimely death."},section:"NEWS: ‘Rival Cult Group Killed Ten on Campus’<br> 	STUDENT: I will definitely need a bullet proof vest before I can go back to the Campus.<br>",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:14,question:"A system of government that listens to public opinion and tolerates opposition is",option:{a:"dictatorial regime",b:"capitalist regime",c:"democratic regime",d:"socialist regime"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:431,question:"Justice demands that people should always do what is",option:{a:"persistently convenient",b:"consistently right",c:"individually acceptable",d:"courageously necessary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:117,question:"Which of the following is the most common forms of drug abuse",option:{a:"drug trafficking",b:"self medication",c:"drug combination",d:"frequent use"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:2,question:"Rule of Law means",option:{a:"supremacy of the law",b:"absence of legal immunity",c:"peace, order and stability",d:"obedience to any authority"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:29,question:"The implication of positive communal relationships is that it",option:{a:"promotes solidarity and love",b:"ensures obedience to constituted authority",c:"encourages ethnic diversity",d:"promotes rural-urban drift."},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:158,question:"The necessary attributes of a state are",option:{a:"resources, population, sovereignty and government",b:"sovereignty, police, army and immigration",c:"definite territory, population, sovereignty and government",d:"Police, Army, sovereignty and custom"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:369,question:"Democracy thrives most where there is",option:{a:"nonpartisan judiciary",b:"freedom of speech and association",c:"absence of universal suffrage",d:"one-party system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:336,question:"Nigeria is a ............. state",option:{a:"Communist",b:"Capitalist",c:"socialist",d:"Feudalist"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:98,question:"What arm of the criminal justice system is prison?",option:{a:"first",b:"second",c:"third",d:"none"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:418,question:"A situation whereby someone is obliged to inform a superior about his actions and decisions for the purpose of control is",option:{a:"probity",b:"self-discipline",c:"accountability",d:"fair play"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:32,question:"The position of the court on this matter justifies the essence of the",option:{a:"rule of law",b:"legislature",c:"police command",d:"separation of powers"},section:"The Bawali High Court has ordered the police in Area Z Command to produce Mr. Zeb, who is in police custody for an alleged offence. The court insists that Mr. Zeb cannot be punished until he is found guilty of breach of any law of the land by a court of competent jurisdiction.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:204,question:"One of the ways to prevent the spread of HIV/AIDs is",option:{a:"Not to eat in fast food joints",b:"Not to shake hands with anybody",c:"To avoid any object contaminated with blood",d:"Sleep under a mosquito net"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:332,question:"The age limit for the service is ..............",option:{a:"25",b:"35",c:"30",d:"18"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:108,question:"The form of government in which the electorate exercise their governing power directly through their elected 	representation is called ........",option:{a:"supremacy",b:"democracy",c:"autocracy",d:"charismatic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:36,question:"From this dialogue, it is very likely that Wanja will be exhibiting the following characters except",option:{a:"disobedience to constituted authority",b:"truancy and perpetual lateness to school",c:"hospitable attitude towards people",d:"arrogance and unruly behaviour."},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:75,question:"The International Court of Justice is located in",option:{a:"Britain.",b:"Netherlands.",c:"Nigeria.",d:"Norway."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:25,question:"Democratic governance is usually characterized by",option:{a:"free, fair and credible elections",b:"buoyant and competitive economy",c:"accessible employment opportunities",d:"youth participation in governance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:139,question:"One of the following is not a federal road agencies",option:{a:"DTO",b:"FRSC",c:"TRACE",d:"VIO"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:240,question:"Drug abuse can be curbed by",option:{a:"encouraging the use of enhancement drugs in sports",b:"teaching youths moral and religious principles",c:"encouraging rural urban migration",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:271,question:"Mr Dickson’s little son, clement was sent away from school because he has not paid his school fees of 	N=11,000. That same day as Mr Dickson boarded a Danfo bus he noticed that the purse of a fellow passenger dropped on the floor of the bus. Mr Dickson tactically picked up the purse, opened it and saw a handsome sum of N=100,000. No body in the bus noticed him, neither did the fellow passenger. As a patriotic and good citizen of Nigeria, what is Mr Dickson expected to do",option:{a:"Pay his tithe (1/10 of the money) to the church take the rest and pray for forgiveness",b:"Draw the attention of the fellow passenger and give the money back to him /her",c:"Use part of the money to pay his son’s fess and keep the rest because opportunity comes but once",d:"Leave the purse on the floor, and mind his business"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:8,question:"Based on the statements above, the decision of the student on having a bullet proof vest shows that cultism",option:{a:"spreads fear and terror.",b:"is a training ground for armed forces.",c:"breeds courageous graduates.",d:"propagates self - defence."},section:"NEWS: ‘Rival Cult Group Killed Ten on Campus’<br> 	STUDENT: I will definitely need a bullet proof vest before I can go back to the Campus.<br>",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:281,question:"Juvenile delinquency refers to",option:{a:"active youths participation in sports",b:"wrong doings by the youths",c:"Refusal to worship God by the youths",d:"Urban Rural migration by the youth"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:167,question:"The following is the function of a responsible parenthood",option:{a:"care and love",b:"gambling",c:"Drug addition",d:"fighting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:67,question:"The right of an individual to seek redress in a law court is categorized under",option:{a:"economic.",b:"political",c:"procedural,",d:"social"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:220,question:"The farthest government to the people is the ............ government",option:{a:"Local",b:"State",c:"Federal",d:"A and B above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:392,question:"Two forms of road signs are regulatory and",option:{a:"punitive",b:"informative",c:"persuasive",d:"inhibitive"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:35,question:"Civil societies are vital for the promotion of popular participation because they are",option:{a:"profit - oriented organizations",b:"engaged in developmental programmes",c:"involved in political education",d:"formidable oppositions to government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:383,question:"Which of the following can not be easily abused?",option:{a:"Cosmetics",b:"Stimulant",c:"Tobacco",d:"Narcotics"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:229,question:"The individual rights would be better protected if enshrined in the ..................",option:{a:"Courts",b:"Constitutions",c:"Bible and Quran",d:"National Newspapers"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:166,question:"The option A4 model was used in the conduct of the",option:{a:"2007 election",b:"1983 election",c:"1993 election",d:"1999 election"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:24,question:"The nearest government to the people and an important means of promoting grassroots development is the",option:{a:"state government",b:"unitary government",c:"local government",d:"federal government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:373,question:"Which of the following is not a form of political participation?",option:{a:"Taking part in voters’ registration exercise",b:"Voting during elections",c:"Joining political party",d:"Ballot box stuffing during elections"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:81,question:"The United Nations universal declaration on human rights was proposed in the year",option:{a:"1925",b:"1930",c:"1946",d:"1948"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:238,question:"The rule of law simply means",option:{a:"The ruling of a lawful leader",b:"The absence of political instability",c:"Supremacy of the law",d:"The ruling of legislators"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:259,question:"The primary duty of the army is to",option:{a:"execute the law",b:"interpret the law",c:"overthrow the government when there is anarchy",d:"defend the country against external aggression"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:268,question:"Political Apathy can lead to",option:{a:"very fast pace of development",b:"the emergence of sound democratic government",c:"wrong set of people coming into power",d:"development of sound political culture"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:286,question:"The Ebola disease is usually acquired when a person comes in contact with",option:{a:"the blood or bodily fluids of an infested organism",b:"anybody whose name is Bola",c:"any animal",d:"snake fish"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:399,question:"In order to avoid undue interference in the process of governance, there should be",option:{a:"clear cut separation of governmental powers",b:"proper fusion of governmental powers and functions",c:"more roles for traditional rulers in the governmental process",d:"additional responsibility for local government council"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:417,question:"Inter-communal relationship is best described as",option:{a:"the interaction between individuals, groups or organizations with common aspirations",b:"the interaction among individuals and professionals in a social setting",c:"loyalty to community leaders so as to achieve rapid communal development",d:"respect for collective national symbols in order to foster nationalistic feeling"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:183,question:"Which of the following is not a duty of a citizen",option:{a:"obedience to the law",b:"payment of taxes",c:"service to the Nation",d:"giving alms to the poor"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:43,question:"A major benefit of youth empowerment is",option:{a:"dependence on foreign aid.",b:"discouragement of patriotism",c:"reduction in crime rate",d:"negation to national prosperity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:187,question:"The following are ways to prevent drug addiction except",option:{a:"civic education",b:"law enforcement and regulation",c:"mass media effort",d:"voting at election"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:434,question:"Ade’s action as shown in the dialogue is a demonstration of political",option:{a:"wisdom",b:"apathy",c:"lawlessness",d:"participation"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:208,question:"The illicit or illegal business in the sales and 	transportation of human beings for economic and other selfish purposes is known as",option:{a:"Human capital development",b:"Human traffic rule disobedience",c:"Human trafficking",d:"Mans inhumanity to man"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:221,question:"An instrument for exercise of power for controlling, administering and managing the affairs of people based on laws is the",option:{a:"Civil service",b:"Executive",c:"Government",d:"State"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:228,question:"It is an offense to drive along the high way",option:{a:"without putting on the seat belt",b:"and talk or smile at the same time",c:"and make phone calls at the same time",d:"A and C above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:26,question:"Political apathy often leads to",option:{a:"low level of participation",b:"good governance",c:"political stability",d:"low literacy level"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:41,question:"One of the major barriers to national development is the",option:{a:"low poverty level",b:"existence of multi - party system",c:"prevalence of corrupt practices",d:"persistent rural - urban migration"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:151,question:"Which of the following is used in gauging public opinion",option:{a:"Constitution",b:"Educational Institution",c:"Mass media",d:"Electoral college"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:83,question:"One of the civic responsibilities of a citizen is to obey",option:{a:"bye-laws.",b:"constituted authority.",c:"court judgments.",d:"edicts."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:236,question:"The lack of interest in politics and political activities by the citizens of a country is known as",option:{a:"political disinterestedness",b:"political culture",c:"political disintegration",d:"political apathy"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:37,question:"Which of the following may result from Wanja’s habit?",option:{a:"Humility for elders",b:"Criminality in the society",c:"Advocacy for hard drugs by NGOs",d:"Excellent performance in school"},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:296,question:"Public servants in Nigeria are expected to be .............",option:{a:"involved in politics",b:"non-partisan",c:"ambitious politically",d:"partial"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"}],n={message:e,subject:o,status:200,total:120,data:a};export{a as data,n as default,e as message,i as status,o as subject,t as total};
